in this video we're going to talk about
how to decompose a function
into two functions
so for instance let's say that
h of x
is equal to the square root of seven x
plus five
express the function h of x
as a composition
of two functions f of x and g of x
such that
h of x is f of g of x
so how can we determine f of x and g of
x given h of x
so notice that f is the function on the
outside and g is the function on the
inside
the stuff on the inside is seven x plus
five
so that's going to be g of x
this stuff on the outside is the square
root symbol and that's gonna be f of x
so f of x is the square root of x so if
we want to determine h of x
which is the composition of f and g
notice that if we take
g
and insert it
into f
that is if we replace this x with seven
x plus five
that will give us h of x
so here's the square root symbol but
without the x so replace the x with
seven x plus five
and that will give us the original
function
but these are the answers that we're
looking for g of x is seven x plus five
and f of x is the square root of x
so let me give you another example that
you can work on
so let's say that
h of x
is one divided by x plus three
go ahead and determine the outside
function
f of x
and also the inside function
g of x
the outside function is going to be one
over x
the inside function is simply x plus
three because if you replace x with x
plus three you're going to get one over
x plus three
and that's pretty straightforward so
these problems are not too bad
let's try another example
so what about this one let's say that
h of x
is the absolute value
of three x plus two
what's the outside function f of x
and the inside function g of x
we can see that on the inside we have
three x plus two so that's g of x
the outside is the absolute value of x
and that's it
and let's do one more example
let's say that h of x
is 2x
cubed plus 7x minus 3
raised to the fourth power
so what's the outside function f of x
and the inside function g of x
on the outside it's x to the fourth
power
on the inside two x cubed plus seven x
minus three
and they go
so that's g of x
and f of x
so that's it for this video thanks again
for watching and have a good day
you